A Guide to the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Association, Inc. records FA085
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Preceding Organizations, 1937-1961, bulk 1952-1958; 1; 3.7 Cubic Feet 11 document cases
  - Consolidation, 1937-1961, bulk 1956-1958; 1956-1958; 1.6; 0.575 Cubic Feet 2 document cases
    - DMA, Inc. - Committee on Lower Manhattan, Inc. - Merger, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 90)
      Includes (but is not limited to): A. Certificate of Consolidation B. List of the D-LMA initial Board of Directors, May 7, 1958 C. Suggested Changes in Agreement for Consolidation (no date) D. Agreement for the Consolidation of CLM, Inc. and DMA, Inc. (2 copies) E. Report of the Committee on Merger of the Committee on Lower Manhattan, Inc. and Downtown Manhattan Association, Inc. (Draft) F. Press Release - Thursday June 5, 1958 - Announces plans to Consolidate the DMA, Inc. and the CLM, Inc. (2 copies) [Jointly released by David Rockefeller (Chairman, Committee on Lower Manhattan, Inc.) and John D. Butt (President, Downtown Manhattan Association, Inc.)]
    - DMA, Inc. - Committee on Lower Manhattan, Inc. - Merger, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 0090A)
      Restricted material.
    - Membership - "D-LMA, Inc. - Schedule of CLM Members Due 1957 and 1958", July 28, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Membership - "D-LMA, Inc. - Schedule of Credits for Dues Paid by DMA Inc. Members as of January 1, 1958", July 16, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - DLMA Vital Records - Corrections and Changes to D-LMA, Inc. By-Laws, June 18, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 93)
      As presented at Board of Directors meeting of June 18, 1958
    - DLMA Vital Records - "Basic Documents", 1937-1961 (Box 11, Folder 94)
      Many of these documents are clearly copies and photocopies. Several are draft versions, some with handwritten notes and changes/alterations of the agreements.
- DLMA, Inc., 1957-1995; 2; 78.875 Cubic Feet 214 document cases
  This series is arranged in 5 subseries, one of which is arranged in 6 sub-subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Corporate Records
  Sub-subseries 1 1 - Corporate Records - Board of Directors Meetings
  Sub-subseries 1 2 - Corporate Records - Members Meetings
  Sub-subseries 1 3 - Corporate Records - Committee Records
  Sub-subseries 1 4 - Corporate Records - Officer's Files
  Sub-subseries 1 5 - Corporate Records - Breakfast Meetings
  Sub-subseries 1 6 - Corporate Records - Financial Records
  Subseries 2 - Membership
  Subseries 3 - Projects
  Subseries 4 - Bulletins and Publications
  Subseries 5 - Reports and Studies
  Series 2 dominates the collection with both its physical size and its presentation of records of enduring research value.
  - Corporate Records, 2.1
    Subseries 1 is arranged in 6 sub-series:
    Sub-subseries 1 1 - Board of Director's Meetings
    Sub-subseries 1 2 - Members Meetings
    Sub-subseries 1 3 - Committee Records
    Sub-subseries 1 4 - Officer's Files
    Sub-subseries 1 5 - Breakfast Meetings
    Sub-subseries 1 6 - Financial Records
    - Board of Director's Meetings, 1958-1995; 2.1.1; 1.225 Cubic Feet 3.5 document cases
      Materials in this sub-subseries are arranged chronologically.
      Records of the Board of Directors meetings are arranged chronologically beginning with the first meeting on June 18, 1958, through April 5, 1995. The meeting records often contain: minutes to the meeting, and approval of the minutes of the previous meeting, agenda, docket, as well as various supporting documents such as annual budgets and progress reports.
      - Board of Directors - First Meeting, June 18, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 95)
      - Board of Directors - Special Meeting, October 7, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 96)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, December 12, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 97)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, October 8, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 98)
      - Board of Directors - Meeting, December 21, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 99)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, April 13, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 100)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, May 9, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 101)
        With verbal Progress Report of Chairman David Rockefeller
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, April 11, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 102)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 5, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 103)
        With verbal Progress Report of David Rockefeller and W. Zucker. Also reports regarding the proposed Civic Center and Battery Park site for the New York Stock Exchange.
      - Board of Directors - Meeting, October 15, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 104)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 4, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 105)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 106)
      - Board of Directors - Special Meeting, June 7, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 107)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 1, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 108)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 7, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 109)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 110)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 4, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 111)
        Discussion regarding World Trade Center and Staggered Work Hours
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 3, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 112)
        Discussion of Mass Transit matters
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 113)
        Reports given regarding the STOL Ports Study; Battery Park City; and Lower Manhattan Developments
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 1, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 114)
        Reports given regarding the Second Avenue Subway; Lower Manhattan Developments; Slide Presentation - Lower Manhattan since 1950
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 115)
        Reports given regarding Battery Park City; Manhattan Landing
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 5, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 116)
        Reports given regarding Federal Hall National Monument; South Street Seaport Museum
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, April 10, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 117)
        David Rockefeller steps down as Chairman of the D-LMA. The Board honored Rockefeller for his leadership since the inception of the Association in 1958. Howard L. Clark was elected as the new Chairman. Reports given regarding the Lower Manhattan Improvement District; West Side Highway Project; Battery Park City
      - Board of Directors - Informal Meeting (in absence of a quorum), February 3, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 118)
        Report given regarding the proposed Convention Center in Battery Park City
      - Board of Directors - Special Meeting, June 15, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 119)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 1, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 120)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 6, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 121)
        The Annual Meeting of February 7, 1978 was adjourned due to inclement weather
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 122)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 5, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 123)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 3, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 124)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 125)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 2, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 126)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 7, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 5, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 4, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 129)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 3, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 130)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 1, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 131)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 7, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 132)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 6, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 133)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 5, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 134)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 3, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 135)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 23, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 136)
        Reports given regarding the Lower Manhattan Project and Plan; the Quality of Life Committee
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, March 1, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 137)
        Report given regarding the Lower Manhattan Plan and BID
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting - Packet, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 138)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting - Potential Directors, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 139)
      - Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, April 5, 1995 (Box 15, Folder 140)
        Report given regarding the Alliance for Downtown New York
    - Members Meetings, 1958-1995; 2.1.2; 0.7 Cubic Feet 2.5 document cases
      Materials in this sub-subseries are arranged chronologically
      Records of the Members meetings are arranged chronologically beginning with the first meeting on October 9, 1958 through April 5, 1995. The meeting records often contain: minutes to the meeting and approval of the minutes of the previous meeting, agenda, docket, as well as various documents supporting the discussion such as financial reports and progress reports.
      - Members - Annual Meeting, October 9, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 141)
        Presentation of the D-LMA's forthcoming "First Report" on Recommended Traffic Improvements, Land Use and Redevelopment Areas in Lower Manhattan
      - Members - Annual Meeting, October 8, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 142)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 143)
        Several topics were briefly discussed including: Heliport; Water Street Widening; West Development Area; World Trade Center. Plans were announced on January 27 for a World Trade Center in the East Development Area bounded by Old Slip, South, Fulton and Water Streets.
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 7, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 144)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 145)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 5, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 146)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 4, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 147)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 148)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 1, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 149)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 7, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 150)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 151)
      - Members - Special Meeting, June 10, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 152)
        10th Anniversary meeting and reception. New scale model of Lower Manhattan exhibited. "Ten Years of Progress" by D-LMA, Inc.
      - Members - Special Meeting, September 9, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 153)
        Report given regarding the Second Avenue Subway. Includes Edmund F. Wagner's statement before the Board of Estimate, August 12, 1968.
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 4, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 154)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 3, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 155)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 156)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 1, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 157)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 158)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 5, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 159)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, April 10, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 160)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 3, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 161)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 1, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 162)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 6, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 163)
        Annual Meeting of February 7, 1978 was adjourned sine die because of the absence of a quorum due to inclement weather.
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 6, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 164)
        Discussion of the D-LMA's December 27, 1978 letter to Governor Carey regarding Battery Park City.
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 5, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 165)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 3, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 166)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, February 2, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 167)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 2, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 168)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 7, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 169)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 5, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 170)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 4, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 171)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 3, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 172)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 1, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 173)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 7, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 174)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 6, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 175)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 5, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 176)
        No minutes
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 3, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 177)
        Includes minutes to the March 5, 1991 meeting.
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 23, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 178)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, March 1, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 179)
      - Members - Annual Meeting, April 5, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 180)
        Report given by Tom Cusick (President, Fifth Avenue Association) regarding the establishment of a Business Improvement District for Lower Manhattan. Also includes several preliminary drafts of the minutes, notes regarding Director selection, etc.
    - Committee Records, 1958-1993; 2.1.3; 5.95 Cubic Feet 13.5 document cases
      Materials are arranged alphabetically by committee name and the meeting dates are then presented chronologically for each committee.
      This subseries contains the meeting records of the Executive Committee; Membership, Organization and Finance Committee; Planning Committee; Public Relations Committee; Real Estate and Traffic and Transportation Committees; and the Sanitation Anti-Litter Task Force. Meeting records often contain: the minutes, agenda, docket, associated reports and various supporting documents.
      - Executive Committee - Meeting, June 11, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 181)
      - Executive Committee - Recommendations to Board of Directors - Fulton Street Widening, June 18, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 182)
      - Executive Committee - Recommendations to Board of Directors - Land Use, Traffic, etc., June 18, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 183)
      - Executive Committee - Recommendations to Board of Directors - Skidmore, Owings & Merrill Redevelopment Report and Lloyd B. Reid, Traffic Engineering Consultant Report, June 18, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 184)
      - Executive Committee - Meeting, September 5, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 185)
      - Executive Committee - Meeting, October 30, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 186)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 3, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 187)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, January 28, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 188)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, April 14, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 189)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, June 15, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 190)
        A Quorum was not present. DLMA retain McKinsey & Company to conduct a study of the desirability and feasibility of establishing a World Trade and Finance Center in the area bounded by Fulton Street, South Street, Old Slip and Water Street as outlined in the McKinsey & Company May 25, 1959 memo entitled "Proposed Study of a World Trade and Finance Center..."
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, July 1, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 191)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, August 11, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 192)
        Includes a report from McKinsey & Company on the progress of its study concerning the desirability and feasibility of establishing a World Trade and Finance Center in the East Re-development Area.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, September 8, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 193)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 17, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 194)
        Report and authorization of further funds for World Trade Center Study (Skidmore, Owings & Merrill; McKinsey & Company; consultant and special legal fees and expenses).
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, February 25, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 195)
        Includes summary of World Trade Center authorizations and expenditures.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, June 14, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 196)
        Includes reports regarding: Broadway Street Lighting, Lower Manhattan Expressway progress, World Trade Center progress, film on Lower Manhattan.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, January 6, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 197)
        Includes a report on the the D-LMA Transportation Study. Also a verbal report was given by the Port of New York Authority regarding the progress of the World Trade Center project.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, June 6, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 198)
        Includes report regarding the Fulton Street widening.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 18, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 199)
        Includes reports regarding: West Side Site for the World Trade Center; Re-Survey of Lower Manhattan.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, February 2, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 200)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, July 10, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 201)
        Includes progress reports regarding: program to renovate historic monuments; Re-Survey of Lower Manhattan, World Trade Center; Lower Manhattan Expressway.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, February 1, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 202)
        Includes reports regarding: Civic Center; New York Stock Exchange Acquisition of Battery Park Site.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, May 7, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 203)
        Committees on Real Estate and Traffic and Transportation jointly recommend items for inclusion in the "Second Report" to be issued in October 1963.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, Jund 11, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 204)
        Land-Use and Traffic recommendations for inclusion in the "Second Report."
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, October 8, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 205)
        Following a presentation of a draft of the "Second Report," its publication was approved by the Committee, and it recommends approval by the Board at its upcoming October 15, 1963 meeting.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, January 29, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 206)
        Includes reports regarding a "Survey of Rapid Transit Needs;" 30-minute WDNT (TV) film on the downtown program.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, March 2, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 207)
        Includes reports regarding: World Trade Center; affiliate arrangement with the Commerce and Industry Association.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, June 15, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 208)
        Includes discussion of Lower Manhattan Expressway.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 21, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 209)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, May 24, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 210)
        Report and approval of a proposed East Side Subway study.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, September 22, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 211)
        Reports regarding: the East Side Subway Study; Lower Manhattan Expressway (oral report).
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, January 6, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 212)
        Includes report regarding the East Side Subway Study.
      - Joint Meeting of the Executive Committee and the Planning Committee, February 11, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 213)
        Meeting called in order to hear a status report on the World Trade Center presented by Austin J. Tobin, Executive Director, The Port of New York Authority.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, June 20, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 214)
        Includes Final Report on the East Side Subway/Water Street Subway by Coverdale & Colpitts.
      - Joint Meeting of the Executive Committee and the Planning Committee, December 7, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 215)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, May 22, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 216)
        Includes report of Historic Sites Committee regarding the Fraunces Tavern block and the South Street Seaport Maritime Museum.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 20, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 217)
        Includes an oral report regarding the Hudson River Landfill project, referred to as the Battery Park City project.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, February 2, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 218)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, April 15, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 219)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, September 24, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 220)
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, January 7, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 221)
        Reports given including: Vollmer Associates study of Lower Manhattan; Planning Committee recommendations regarding Battery Park City and U.S. Assay Office.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, May 2, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 222)
        Oral reports given regarding: Battery Park City; Bowling Green Summer Band Concerts; Establishment of a Commercial High School; Recommendations of the Public Relations Committee on official release of D-LMA "Third Report;" D-LMA "Fact Book."
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 17, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 223)
        Oral reports given regarding: subway matters; staggered work hours proposal.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, May 13, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 224)
        Reports given regarding: Staggered Work Hours program; Development of Downtown Brooklyn; Second Avenue Subway and Bowling Green Station; proposed annex to Whitney Museum.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, August 7, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 225)
        Report on meeting with Mayor Lindsay; consideration of proposed study for STOLport in Lower Manhattan.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 4, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 226)
        Reports given regarding: STOLport Feasibility Study; Proposed West Side Development District.
      - Joint Meeting of the Executive Committee and the Planning Committee, February 10, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 227)
        Meeting called in order to hear a presentation by Robert S. Weinstein, Director, Office of Lower Manhattan Development, regarding a proposed Lower Manhattan People Mover.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, February 24, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 228)
        Reports given regarding: People Mover; STOLport progress.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, July 1, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 229)
        Reports given regarding: People Mover; Housing Potential Study; Battery Park City.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 13, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 230)
        Oral reports given regarding: Housing Potential Study; East River area development; Second Avenue Subway; People Mover.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, June 15, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 231)
        Oral reports given regarding: Manhattan Landing; Second Avenue Subway and Bowling Green Station; People Mover; Preparation of the D-LMA "Fourth Report."
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, August 1, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 232)
        Oral reports given regarding: Manhattan Landing and Battery Park City; Second Avenue Subway; West Side Highway; Proposal for D-LMA "Fourth Report."
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, September 22, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 233)
        Recommendations regarding: possible relocation of the Baruch School of Business and Public Administration; improved street lighting.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, December 8, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 234)
        Several reports and discussion points including: relocation of Baruch School of Business and Public Administration; Lower Manhattan Landing; Commuter Transportation Study, etc.
      - Executive Committee - Special Meeting, May 8, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 235)